A Guide to the Fairhope Single Tax Corporation Community Engravings & Artwork 17th through 19th centuries
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Fairhope Single Tax Corporation Community Engravings & Artwork 17th through 19th centuries
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10517-c
This collection consists of ca. 550 engravings and prints (one Hollinger box and 17 Oversize folders).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by the Fairhope Single Tax Corporation, Fairhope, Alabama on March 30, 2001, through Paul Gaston.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 550 engravings and prints (1 Hollinger box and 17 OS folders) from the Fairhope Single Tax Corporation community, dating from the 17th to the 19th centuries. The engravings were acquired by Marie Howland, assistant editor of the Fairhope newspaper. The collection contains engravings, a few of which may be originals; restrikes; 19th century reprints from magazines and books; some original art work and tissue paper tracings, both presumably by Howland; and photographs.
Photographs include faded portraits of Lord Palmerston, Lord Lyndhurst, William Walker with original autograph, and the Rev. Dr. Marvine; a few small snapshots of Swiss scenes and a large one of a glacier; and one mounted scene of four women in front of a Victorian gingerbread house.
Miscellaneous items include pages from a souvenir book from the 1889 Paris Exposition, and oversize engravings of prominent Protestant Reformation figures from a book. Individual portrait engravings include European nobility and rulers; popes; Christian saints; artists, such as Gilbert Charles Stuart; authors such as John Milton and William Shakespeare; scientists, like Sir Isaac Newton; explorers, like Sir Walter Raleigh; and philosophers.
Arrangement
The items in the collection are arranged first by the type of illustration and size and then by subject matter.
Contents List
- Book Illustrations n.d.
- Book Illustrations from Hesiod's Works and Days translated by C.A. Elton [ca. 1832?]
- Drawings n.d.
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Animals [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Buildings & Landscapes [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Classical Figures & Scenes [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Domestic Scenes [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Individual Portraits [18th & 19th centuries], (2 folders)
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Inscriptions [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Military & Travel Scenes [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Miscellaneous & Fragments [18th & 19th centuries]
- Engravings, Copies & Restrikes - Religious & Biblical Scenes [18th & 19th centuries]
- Illustrations, Chiefly Engravings [17th & 18th centuries]
- Tracings of Artwork n.d.
- Watercolors n.d.
- Drawings and Watercolor 1951, n.d. (Oversize Folder 1)
- Engravings - Individuals and Miscellaneous 1870, n.d. (Oversize Folder 2)
- Engravings - Protestant Reformation Figures from a Book n.d. (Oversize Folder 3)
- Engravings of Landscapes 1793-1854,n.d. (Oversize Folder 4)
- Engravings - Classical & Mythological Scenes 1739, n.d. (Oversize Folder 5)
- Engravings - Religious & Biblical Scenes 1648-1806 (Oversize Folder 6)
- Engravings - Portraits 1648-1835 (Oversize Folder 7)
- Engravings by Jean Holbein 1790-1795 (Oversize Folder 8)
- Book Illustrations 1864, n.d. (Oversize Folder 9)
- Drawings n.d. (Oversize Folder 10)
- Tracings of Artwork n.d. (Oversize Folder 11)
- Illustrations for Paris Exposition Souvenir Book 1889 (Oversize Folder 12)
- Photographs n.d. (Oversize Folder 13)
- Engravings - Miscellaneous Scenes, includng some from Shakespeare and Classical Subjects n.d. (Oversize Folder 14)
- Engravings - Religious and Biblical Subjects n.d. (Oversize Folder 15)
- Printed Pages from Gallery of Masterpieces of the Old German Wood Engravers1858/9? (Oversize Folder 16)
- Diploma awarded to Maria S. Case from the New York City Normal School 1859 (Oversize Folder 17)